I am a reformed marketer,
لدى خبرة في مجال الإصلاح التسويقي،
and I now work in international development.
وحالياً يتعلق مجال عملي بالتنمية الدولية.
In October, I spent some time in the Democratic Republic of Congo,
خلال شهر أكتوبر الماضي، أمضيت أياماً في جمهورية الكنغو الديمقراطية،
which is the [second] largest country in Africa.
وهي ثاني أكبر الأقطار في القارة الأفريقية.
In fact, it's as large as Western Europe,
تقدر مساحتها بحجم الإتحاد الأوروبي،
but it only has 300 miles of paved roads.
إلا أن الطرق الممهدة فيها لا تتجاوز ال(300) أميال فقط.
The DRC is a dangerous place.
وتعد الكنغو من الأمكنة المحفوفة بالمخاطر.
In the past 10 years, five million people have died
خلال العقد الماضي، لقى نحو خمسة مليون شخص حتفهم
due to a war in the east.
جراء الحرب التي إندلعت شرقي البلاد.
But war isn't the only reason
بيد أن الحرب ليست المسوغ الوحيد
that life is difficult in the DRC.
لتعذر أسباب العيش فيها.
There are many health issues as well.
فثمة مهددات صحية كبرى ماثلة أيضاً.
In fact, the HIV prevalence rate
إذ أن معدلات تفشي وباء الأيدز
is 1.3 percent among adults.
في أوساط الراشدين تمثل نسبة (1.3%).
This might not sound like a large number,
قد يتبين وكأنه معدل غير كبير،
but in a country with 76 million people,
ولكن في دولة ذات (76) مليون نسمة،
it means there are 930,000 that are infected.
فهذا يعني بأن هنالك (930) ألف مصاب.
And due to the poor infrastructure,
وكنيجة لضعف الإمكانيات،
only 25 percent of those
يتسنى لنحو (25%) فقط من هذه الشريحة
are receiving the life-saving drugs that they need.
الحصول على العقاقير التي يحتاجوها لتمديد فترات الحضانة للمرض.
Which is why, in part,
وهذا يفسر، بطريقة أو بأخرى،
donor agencies provide condoms
تهافت المنظمات الطوعية لتقديم الواقيات
at low or no cost.
بتكلفة أقل أو بالمجان.
And so while I was in the DRC,
ولذا إستغليت تواجدي بالكنغو،
I spent a lot of time talking to people about condoms,
للترويج بإسهاب عن الواقيات الذكرية،
including Damien.
بما فيهم داميان.
Damien runs a hotel outside of Kinshasa.
الذي كان يدير فندقاً خارج كنشاسا.
It's a hotel that's only open until midnight,
يفتح أبوابه للنزلاء حتي منتصف الليل فقط،
so it's not a place that you stay.
لذا فهو الأمكنة التى يتعذر عليك الإقامة فيه.
But it is a place where sex workers and their clients come.
لأنه يمثل بؤرة لإلتقاء بائعات الهوى بزبائنهن.
Now Damien knows all about condoms,
وداميان هذا أصبح ملماً بكل فوائد الواقيات المجانية،
but he doesn't sell them.
ومع ذلك يجد صعوبة في توزيعها.
He said there's just not in demand.
ويؤكد بأنها غير محبذة للنزلاء.
It's not surprising,
ولا غرابة في ذلك،
because only three percent of people in the DRC
إذ أن (3%) فقط من سكان الكنغو يقدمون على
use condoms.
إستخدام الواقيات.
Joseph and Christine,
جوزيف و كريستين،
who run a pharmacy where they sell a number of these condoms,
اللذان يديران صيدلية تباع فيها تلك الواقيات ،
said despite the fact that donor agencies provide them at low or no cost,
يؤكدان بأنه على الرغم من حصولهم عليها من منظمات العون بتكلفة أقل أو مجاناً،
and they have marketing campaigns that go along with them,
مصحوبة ببرنامجها التسويقي الذي يتماشي معهن،
their customers don't buy the branded versions.
فرواد الصيديلة لا يجذبهم هذا الصنف من الواقيات.
They like the generics.
وإنما يميلون لشراء الأصناف الأخرى.
And as a marketer, I found that curious.
وبحكم مهنتي، فقد إسترعي الأمر جل إهتمامي.
And so I started to look at what the marketing looked like.
فتحولت إلى إجراء دراسة على الجانب التسويقي.
And it turns out that there are three main messages
تبين فيما بعدها بأن هنالك ثلاث كلمات شائعة
used by the donor agencies for these condoms:
رسمتها المنظمات المانحة على صناديق الواقيات:
fear, financing and fidelity.
الخطر، والتمويل، والصحة.
They name the condoms things like Vive, "to live"
لقد أطلقوا عليها مسميات تجارية مثل عِش
or Trust.
أو ثِق.
They package it with the red ribbon
منقوش علي المنتج شريط أحمر
that reminds us of HIV,
للإيحاء بمرض الأيدز،
put it in boxes that remind you who paid for them,
إسم بعثة (يونميل) مطبوع على الصناديق للإشارة إلى الجهة المانحة،
show pictures of your wife or husband
طبع صور للزوجة أو الزوج
and tell you to protect them
للإيحاء بحماية الأسرة
or to act prudently.
أو التصرف بمسؤولية.
Now these are not the kinds of things that someone is thinking about
علماً بأن هذه الأشياء في مجملها لا تخطر على بال شخص
just before they go get a condom.
أراد شراء الواقي الذكري.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What is it that you think about
وما الشيء الذي يسيطر على تفكيرك
just before you get a condom?
قبيل توجهك لشراء العازل الذكري؟
Sex!
الجنس!
And the private companies that sell condoms in these places,
والشركات الخاصة المستفيدة من بيع الواقيات في هذه المناطق،
they understand this.
لديها دراية تامة بالأمر.
Their marketing is slightly different.
لذا فهم يتبنون نمطاً تسويقياً مختلفاً.
The name might not be much different,
قد لا تختلف مسمياتهم التجارية كثيراً عن المنظمات المانحة،
but the imagery sure is.
ولكن يكمن الفرق في عكس الصور.
Some brands are aspirational,
بعض العلامات التجارية طموحة جداً،
and certainly the packaging is incredibly provocative.
بحيث يتم تغليفها بصورة جاذبة للغاية.
And this made me think
وهذا ما حداني إلى الظن
that perhaps the donor agencies had just missed out
بطبيعة الشيء الذي غفلت عنه المنظمات الطوعية
on a key aspect of marketing:
والمتعلق بأهم عناصر العملية التسويقة:
understanding who's the audience.
تفهم مزاج المستهلكين.
And for donor agencies, unfortunately,
وللأسف, كانت شريحة المستهلكين
the audience tends to be
بالنسبة للوكالات الطوعية
people that aren't even in the country they're working [in].
عبارة عن أشخاص مختلفين عما سواهم
It's people back home,
كشعوب بلادهم
people that support their work,
أشخاص يريدون تدعيم أعمالها
people like these.
كهؤلاء.
But if what we're really trying to do
ولكن إذا رغبنا فعلياً
is stop the spread of HIV,
في وقف إنتشار مرض الأيدز،
we need to think about the customer,
فيتعين علينا أن نفكر في مزاج المستهلك،
the people whose behavior needs to change --
تلكم الشريحة التي تحتاج إلى تغير مفاهيمها --
the couples,
الأزواج،
the young women, the young men --
الشابات، والشباب --
whose lives depend on it.
والذين تتوقف حياتهم كلية على ذلك.
And so the lesson is this:
ولذا فهذا هو الدرس:
it doesn't really matter what you're selling;
لا يهم كثيراً ما هية الشيء الذي تسوقه:
you just have to think about who is your customer,
فجل ما عليك فعله هو تفهم عقلية المستهلك،
and what are the messages
وما هي الرسائل الكفيلة
that are going to get them to change their behavior.
بحثهم على تغير سلوكياتهم
It might just save their lives.
لأنها قد ستساهم في تغيير حياتهم
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)